[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
let's just review what happens if we
have some quantum mechanical problem
involving some discrete variable that
could take on some values uh finite
number of values from one to n or
something like
that little
n little n could be a discrete VAR
variable going from 1 2 3 four and so
forth up to some
number uh something that we can
measure and if we measure it we'll get a
number and that number will have a
probability the probability let's call P
of
n standard rule the sum of the
probabilities should add up to one total
probabilities should add up to one and
so always sum of probabilities should
add up to
one that's one rule another rule related
to it not completely disconnected is
that probabilities are governed by
amplitudes amplitudes are related to the
inner product of State vectors with
other state vectors let's just write
down one or two Simple Rules first of
all the basis vectors that are
associated with n let's call them M and
N can be taken to form an orthonormal
basis that means each of the vectors has
length
one and they're mutually orthogonal and
that we can summarize by writing that
that's equal to Delta nn the chronical
Delta symbol which is 1 if n is equal to
M and zero if it's not now we can always
think of Delta
NM which looks like it's a function of
two variables two discrete variables we
can always think of it as really a
function of only one discrete variable
namely n minus M we could call it Delta
of n minus M with the rule that when n
minus m is anything but zero
Delta of n minus m is equal to
z f n- m is not equal to zero and Delta
of n minus
m is equal to 1 if N - M is equal to
zero so in fact Delta of n minus m is a
function of two variables but it has a
particular form and it's really only a
function of the difference between them
zero if there's a difference non zero if
there's not a difference I just point
that out as something to uh to keep in
mind if
we if we plot the probability as a
function of n then it has its values on
the integers and so it one integer it
may be one value another integer it may
be another value another
integer and so forth and so on and it's
these Heights which add up to one that's
the picture for a discrete
variable if like the position of a
particle if the variable that we're
measuring is continuous if it can take
on any real number for example or take
on some value over a range of real
numbers perhaps from 0 to one or more
simply any real number altogether then
we have to change the rules a little bit
we have to think a little bit what we're
doing it doesn't make sense to ask
what's the probability that the
coordinate of a particle is
three the probability that it's exactly
three exactly three oh boy we're getting
oh this is a fancy
uh please come and uh come and join
me I I I will have some uh the
probability
that a continuous variable is equal to
any exact particular number is
infinitely small a particular number is
a set of measures
zero uh and so the probability for any
particular
value is
zero but what we speak about is the
probability that the position for
example is somewhere in some range of
values and we we Define a probability
Den it the probability density let's
call it let's still continue to call it
P it's a probability density as a
function of X and it's a continu
typically is a continuous
function for some reason I don't seem to
have any decent pin tonight all right so
it's typically some uh some continuous
function could be something like that
course it doesn't have to be a
bell-shaped curve like that it could
have bumps and so forth but a
bell-shaped Curve will illustrate the
point and we don't ask what's the
probability that if we looked for the
particle we would find it exactly at
some value of x we ask what's the
probability that we would find it on an
interval on some interval between X and
X Plus Delta X let's say an interval of
width Delta X we Define the probability
density so that the probability itself
is given by the integral of the
probability
density over the intergral from X to X
Plus Delta
X that
integral that sum of infinitely small
probabilities but there's an infinite
number of them in there that's the
probability let's call it the total
probability to find the particle between
X and X Plus Delta X I'm making up
notation as I go along I may not even
use it again but uh but that's the idea
in that case the first equation up there
the sum Over N of P of n gets replaced
and it gets replaced by Let's uh let's
put it up there it gets replaced
by the integral
DX of the probability density is equal
to one
right so that's the first replacement we
have to
make now um what about the inner
products between basis vectors ah before
we talk about that we should talk about
the Delta
function the Delta function is a useful
tool for studying
um analoges of these equations for
continuous variables BAS basically it's
the continuous version of the chronica
Delta
symbol that's what it is it's the
continuous version of the chronica Delta
symbol for variables for a variable for
a single variable X which is continuous
again it can be thought of as a function
of the difference of the variables so
let's the direct Delta
function Delta function
let's think of it as a function of two
variables X and Y but it's really a
function only of the difference between
them Delta of xus
Y and it's defined so that it's
zero If X is not equal to
Y just like the chronica
Delta and what is it when X is equal to
y
the answer I'm not going to give because
the answer is undefined but if you want
to think about it
um qualitatively we draw the x-axis
here's the point Y and think of Y as a
parameter now just think of Y is fixed
this is a this is a function of X which
varies as you vary X and as long as X is
not equal to Y it's zero but when X hits
y it gets very large
not one but very
large it's defined in such a way that
the area under the Delta function under
this spike is equal to
one the area under the spike is equal to
one so it's defined so that Delta that
the integral of Delta of x -
y
DX doesn't depend at all on
y it's just equal to
one now is there any real function which
does that no no honest to goodness
mathematically well- defined function
can be zero everywhere except at one
point that's okay it can be zero
everywhere except at one point but have
an area which is equal to one if it has
an area which equal to
one well it must be infinitely High
but we can approximate it or we can
think of it as a as the limit of a
sequence of
approximations of functions which have a
width let's call it Epsilon and a
height 1/
Epsilon now a mathematician would never
accept this as the actual definition he
would say the limit doesn't exist the
limit just just doesn't exist okay what
a mathematician would say is a little
bit different he would say the Delta
function is defined in the the following
way it's not really a function it's an
operation which you do to
functions what do you do to functions
with a Delta function you integrate it
Delta of x-
Y with functions of
X in other words whenever you see the
Delta
function it's something to be
integrated with a function of X again
think of Y is just a parameter y could
be zero in which case it would just be
the integral of Delta of x f ofx or Y
could be one in which case it would be
Delta of x -1 * F ofx and so
forth the Delta function is defined in a
particular way so that this is equal to
something particular but in order to
let's let's use this um intuitive
picture of the Delta function to
motivate what the answer to this
integral is this is integral DX
all right first of all the answer can
only depend on F at xal y it cannot
depend on F anywhere except x equal y
because the function that it's being
folded in with vanishes everywhere
except that x equals y so here's a way
to think about it supposing here's this
is this point is the point Y we have
some function f of
x and the value of the the function away
from this point is quite irrelevant to
the
integral because when we multiply F ofx
by the Delta function the Delta function
is zero on both sides here and only the
value of the function in this narrow
interval can be
important now assume that the function
in this narrow interval is continuous
and so it doesn't vary very much in fact
it varies negligibly over the tiny range
Epsilon and as Epsilon goes to zero the
function will vary less and less over
the range
Epsilon and so if that's the case we
might as well just evaluate F ofx at the
point Y we won't be making a mistake uh
in the integral because the integral is
only sensitive to F at the point Y so
this must be equal then to the integral
well let's just do it in steps Delta of
x - y f of Y
DX but an integral over
X we can take F of Y on the
outside let's just take it on the
outside since it doesn't it doesn't
depend on X at
all it just becomes F of
Y and now we use the fact or the
assumption that the integral of Delta of
x - y DX is just equal to one and the
result is of course just the
rule this is the rule now which defines
the Delta function it is not really a
function it's an operation that you do
on a function but whatever that
operation is it always gives just F at
the point Y that's basically its
definition from a mathematical point of
view an operation that you do on a
function that gives the value of the
function at the point Y I don't find
that terribly satisfying I find it much
more satisfying to intuitively think of
it as a very high narrow
function with area one with total area
one
uh anyway that's the Delta that's the
Delta function now let's come back to
the particle on a line and ask what's
the analog of the inner
product
of the nth State Vector with the M State
Vector now n and M are replaced by the
position of a
particle and
so the natural question is if the state
vectors of the system are spanned that
means if there's a basis of State
vectors labeled with the coordinate
position x and x is a continuous
variable then we can ask what is the
inner product between X and Y
the answer is they're orthogonal If X is
not equal to y That's the basic rule
that if two configurations are
measurably different then the inner
product should be zero it's the analog
of Delta MN equals z if n is not equal
to M but if x is equal to Y it shouldn't
be
zero the natural analog is to set it
equal to Delta of x -
y now notice that means that the normal
at the norm of the vector XX itself is
not really defined it's really the Delta
function at the origin it's the Delta
function at the point x equals y and so
it's infinitely high in fact we never
actually wind up using this quantity we
always wind up using it in this form as
you'll see I'll give you some
examples but that's what
replaces the in a product
structure uh that's there for discrete
spaces for spaces with a discret basis
uh of
vectors all right now let's go back and
uh discuss the rules of probability we
don't need this anymore let's go back
and discuss the rules of probability in
quantum
mechanics and how they're
related to these abstract
definitions first in the discrete space
space in a discrete space the
probability in a particular state if we
have a particular State that's been
prepared the probability p r o b
probability the
probability that a measurement will
yield the value in is given by if if s
is the state of the system and we're
going to talk about preparing States
making them and so forth but for the
moment SII is the state of the system
it's a vector in the vector space
it's in a product with the discrete
State n is called the probability
amplitude for the state n but it is not
the probability we have to take its
absolute value and square it another way
of writing it is that it's s in times
its own complex conjugate which can be
written as s
n n s not
summed no sum over
n that's the probability to uh detect if
you like the value n for the observable
that's labeled by
n what's the natural analog of that the
natural analog for discreet uh for
discret Sy sorry for continuous systems
is that the probability density let's
call it P of X now or P let's call it P
of Y why does does not represent a
different coordinate from X they just
represent two values X and Y represent
two
values of the same variable is the the
line that the particle is moving on
let's call this point x and let's call
this point Y it's not the X and Y AIS
it's all a horizontal axis and this
corresponds to two distinct points the
probability that we find the particle at
Y in a given State now how is a state
described it's described in terms of of
a function of X but let's just uh let's
just write it it's given by the inner
product of the state Vector of the
system with the state in which the
particle is known to be at
y sorry that's not this probability
that's the thing which you square to get
the
probability this thing
squared which is also equal to s y y
s but that now raises the question how
do we calculate the inner product of s
with
Y now the vector space that we're
dealing with is the vector space of
functions of
X each Vector is described or labeled in
terms of a function s of x a wave
function wave functions like this which
are complex functions which depend on a
single variable form a vector space so
they form a candidate for the
description of a
particle and we've already discussed the
inner product in this space the inner
product in the space let me just write
it down the inner product between two
vectors fi and
S is just equal to the integral
DX F star of x s of
X the definition of the inner product so
now we can apply it to
calculating y
s let's just do it it's
equal to the integral
DX s of
X and now the wave function associated
with a particle known to be at
y that wave function is just Delta of
xus
y a particle known to be at y its wave
function is zero unless X is equal to Y
and the Delta function if sorry it's
zero unless X is yeah I said it right
unless X is equal to Y so the F Vector
here is just Delta of x - Y and it says
the amplitude well it's it says what it
says just just the wave function where
did I write it over there so this is the
wave function of a particle known to be
at y remember think of Y as a parameter
and X is a variable and this is the wave
function of a particle known to be at
y0 unless X is equal to Y okay we know
the rule for calculating this integral
is just to substitute for X the value y
That's the definition of the Delta
function that's just equal to S of
Y so here's what we found we found found
that the probability
amplitude for detecting the particle at
Y is nothing but the wave function s of
Y we've already said that previously but
I'm just describing it in a more formal
mathematical rigorous uh way that the
amplitude to discover the particle at
point Y is given by the inner product of
s with Y and it just is the wave
function at point Y from that we
immediately follow follows that the
probability
density is just
equal the S star of
y s of
Y all right so that's applying the
axioms to a particle moving on an axis
on a continuous axis and the only really
new thing is that we have to uh that we
have to deal with the Continuum of igen
value values or the Continuum of
possibilities by substituting for the
chronica Delta the dra
Delta any questions yeah yes can you go
back to the the first statement of the
top of that board there go through again
please oh this is this is uh this
is one of the postulates of quantum
mechanics the probability if we have a
discrete set of possibilities
all right a discrete set of
possibilities could mean heads or tails
if it were a d it could mean one through
six if it were uh some other variable
which could take on any of a discrete
number of variables then for each value
of that variable for each possibility
for each independent possibility there's
a state Vector a bra vector and a k
Vector labeled
n one of the PO one of the one of the
postulates of Quant one of the four or
five postulates that I gave you the last
time for quantum mechanics is that the
probability to
detect igen value in I'll use the word
igen value n or that the observable has
value in is the inner product of the
state Vector whatever the state Vector
happens to be with the basis Vector N
squared okay that's just this times it's
complex conjugate so i n that's this and
here's the complex
conjugate
okay okay all right now it's just a
matter of substitution a matter of
formal substitution wherever you see in
Stick
y instead of thinking about discrete
probabilities think about probability
densities things that we will integrate
in order to find probabilities this is
now the probability density
replace probability by probability
density replace n by
y up till then no
difference and then in a
moment we will uh discuss
that okay added ingredient that the
inner product
structure that we postulated for this
for the vector space of functions
particular complex functions was just to
integrate over x f star with s okay
that's a that's another posture if you
like another um Assumption of quantum
mechanics point is it works of course
and it leads to a nice uh set of
ideas okay so then we can calculate the
inner product of
s with the vector representing the
particle localized at y it's just given
by the integral of the wave function of
the particle
so I of x times the wave function
describing a particle known to be at y
known to be localized exactly at y
That's this Delta function this High
narrow function which is zero
everywhere's except that xals Y and has
area under it equal to one that's the
Delta function that integral is just s
of y definition of the Delta
function so if we know that y of s is
sorry Y in a product with s is just the
wave function s of Y we can use that in
here and we see that the probability is
just s star
s we could have we could have begun with
this it would have been fine to begin
with this and work in some other
direction but this is the basic
um
uh set of rules set of postulates for
quantum mechanics that dra laid
out uh uh I don't know 1930 somewhere
somewhere around has never been replaced
by anything it still stands today
exactly the way he uh the way he
expressed
it yeah
understand well do you understand do you
understand
said okay let's okay good let's let's
check and prove that Delta of x- Y is
the igen function of the operator x with
I value Y is that what you're asking no
I don't understand that's not what you
haveu no the inner yeah the inner
product is a number but it depends on
which X and which are come back to here
direct Delta function it's the direct
Delta
function it's the direct Delta
function on the right sign is a function
then so is the x is is a variable on the
left side so it's no the thing on the
right side is one if it's not one it's
infinite if xal y
Sorry by by the vectors themselves
having an infinite length by the vectors
having an infinite
length now if you really want to do this
right and we it would take us another
two hours to do it right what you really
do is you replace the continuous line by
a dense set of points a dense set of
discrete
points okay and instead separated by a
tiny distance
a then instead of labeling the particle
by a position on the line we might label
it
by which site it's at which of these n
sites it's
at okay we could take we could then
use the standard definition delta
NM the implication of this is that the
inner product of one of these with
itself is just
one okay what we would do to get to the
vectors
X is to multiply the vectors
n by a numerical value which would be 1
over the square
root of
a you just multiply the vectors by a
large number when a gets small the one
over theare root of a gets big and you
simply multiply all of the vectors what
I'm this x here means
X can be identified with n it's simply
the coordinate position of a Point
located n units down the line okay the
vector X is 1 over the < TK of a * n
that's the official definition the way
things are way things are set up but
then if you take the inner product of X
with
Y what you'll get is Delta of n minus m
all right that's n minus m y here
corresponds to the m site X corresponds
to the N site divided by
a well when a gets to be a very very
small number this inner product becomes
infinite or just very large if you like
just very
large and that's the limit in which this
becomes Delta of xus Y
um you can work everywhere if you like
with with a discrete space like this but
it's useful this is a useful definition
the point is this is a useful definition
let me show you something else when you
integrate when you integrate P of X
DX that's not really the
sum that's not equal the to the sum of P
of X it's equal to the
what's the relationship between the
integral of a function of a smooth
variable and the corresponding discret
sum well the answer is that the integral
is the sum times Delta
x p of X time Delta X where each little
Delta X here that gives you an area the
height times the width and the integral
is the limmit of the sum of P of X time
Delta X or just times
a so you see this little a interval gets
into
equations it gets into
equations uh it gets into this equation
in this
form and it gets
into this equation in this
form this is what we're doing this is
what we're doing let's see can we uh do
a little bit better than that
[Music]
um well I think if you trace it through
you'll find out that the definitions are
completely consistent with this and this
a here is the same as this a here so
we're just taking all of the vectors and
stretching them out by a distance one
over the square root of a if we stretch
them out by distance one over square
root of a then all the inner products
get to be very big now remember this
Delta function what here look here's
another way to think about it what is
Delta function it's a high narrow
function it's a high narrow function
whose width can just be taken to be a
and whose height is one over
a all right let's uh let's uh take that
definition of the Delta function its
width is a and its height is 1 over
a
okay now here I've told you that I've
stretched every every every Vector out
by 1 over the < TK of a so we can now
calculate what the inner product of X
with Y is it's just Delta of n minus m /
a but this is just a Delta function it's
a function which is zero everywhere
except when X is y or when n is equal to
M and there it's of height 1/
a Okay so we've just stretched the
vectors out for convenience mostly for
convenience we've stretched them out by
this Factor 1 /un of A and then the
inner product goes from being the
chronica Delta to being the direct Delta
the direct Delta differs from the
chronical Delta if we you know if we
approximate The Continuous situation by
a very very dense collection of points
then the chronica Delta and the direct
Delta simply differ by a factor of one
over the
spacing and if we put that factor of one
over the spacing into the definition of
the vectors here then we come out to the
nice formal
um uh convention that the inner product
of X with Y is Delta of xus Y you don't
ever really have to do this it's just a
nice tool
for for um
eliminating lots of dependence on this
small variable
a okay
so that's the particle on a line or the
wave function for a particle on a line
the wave function is a probability
amplitude and it plays the same role as
n
s in discrete quantum
mechanics all right let's study another
system let's study a system of a
particle moving on a circular line on a
circular line meaning a circle circular
line means a
circle here's our
Circle and there's a particle on it
somewhere now I'm going to lay out this
circle I'm going to cut the circle up
here or someplace no I guess maybe I'll
cut the circle uh uh down here cut it
down here and take the entire
circumference of it and sort of lay it
out on a
line just to think of it uh as a line
interval instead of a circle what's the
difference between a line and well let's
let's let's come through in a moment
instead of labeling the circle with an
angle I'm going to label it with a
coordinate X let's take the radius of
the circle to be R and the total
circumference of the circle is 2 pi r
that means if I lay the circle out on a
line it goes from 0 to 2 pi
r the particle can be found anywhere on
this line interval or equivalently
anywhere is on this circle so how do we
represent vectors how do we represent
the space of states the space of states
is again labeled by position but now X
only goes from 0 to 2i R
precisely the same setup eventually we
come to the idea of a wave function s of
x the square of which is the probability
for finding the particle at different
positions we come again to the idea of a
probability amplitude to find the
particle at different locations and the
square of this when I say the square I
mean the absolute value of the square
the absolute value of the square of this
is the thing which represents the
probability on this axis but there's one
thing we have to take into account if we
really want to think about it as
something on a circle if something is on
a circle if a function is defined on a
circle then it has the property that
when you go all the ways around the
function comes back to itself if a
function is defined on a line interval
that is not necessarily so so in order
to be studying a particle on a circle we
have to restrict ourselves to wave
functions which are periodic which means
they come back to themselves after going
from 0 to 2i R another way to say that
is that the space the vector space that
we're talking about is the space of
function s of X which have the
property that they're equal to S of x +
2 pi
r consider the class of functions the
special class of functions which when
they start at zero and get to 2 pi r
they come back to the same value they're
called periodic
functions okay special class of
functions first question is are they a
vector space the first thing you should
think of to yourself is am I following
the rules of quantum mechanics is this a
vector space well if we take a function
which comes back to itself and we
multiply it by a constant any complex
constant it will still be a function
which comes back to itself a periodic
function when you multiply it by a
constant is still periodic what happens
if you add two periodic functions Each
of which comes back to itself after
going around the circle the sum of two
periodic functions are still periodic so
the periodic functions are a vector
space an allowable Vector space for
studying a quantum mechanical
system
that's that would be be the
basic setup for quantum mechanics on a
periodic interval or equivalently
quantum mechanics on a
circle okay the last time we began to
study momentum so let's come back to
momentum thus far we've been studying
position let's come to
momentum the position operator as I
explained to you last time
is equivalent to multiplication of a
function of X by by X itself it takes
any function of X and multiplies it by X
so it's an operation that you do on the
vector space that multiplies it by
X I'm interested now in the
momentum
operator the operator which represents
momentum we discussed it last time let's
call it
P and we discussed it last time it's
I
minus times d by
DX now what this really means is that
the abstract operator when it acts on
abstract vectors has the same action as
minus i d by DX or minus i h d by DX
when it acts on functions of X there's a
one: one correspondence between vectors
and
functions and the things that you can do
to a function are to differentiate it
multiply it by something and so forth so
every operator corresponds to an
operation that you do on a
function and this is the definition or
this is the operation that you would
do uh to Define momentum well we worked
out the igen vectors of this operator
the igen vector were just defined by
minus i h Bar D by
DX I of X is equal to k k is the igen
value s of
x uh no p s of
X momentum not probability here momentum
let's call yeah let's sry it's p for
momentum what's the solution of this
equation the solution of this equation
is s of x
is equal to any numerical multiple
incidentally time e to the
i p over
HR * X let's check that if I
differentiate with respect to X it pulls
down a factor of
i p over H bar I multiply by H bar that
gets rid of the H bar and then I
multiply by minus I that gets rid of the
I so this
operation when it when it hits s of x if
this is s of X let's call it s p ofx it
means the wave function associated with
a particle of momentum P the wave
function associated with a particle of
momentum p is e to the i p over H bar X
all right to check that what we do is we
check that the S of X is an igen Vector
of the appropriate operator now why this
is called momentum is another question
as I emphasized last time to check that
this makes any sense to call it momentum
we want to understand how classical how
wave packets move we want to understand
how wave packets for heavy objects move
and we want to check that the motion of
the wave packet is consistent with
calling this object momentum but for the
time being this is just a name momentum
is just a name for the observable that
goes with this oper Ator here are its
igen values all possible real numbers
and here are the igen
functions it's
traditional to put a square
root okay let's uh let's be careful now
we're doing particle on a
circle let's
consider the inner product of this wave
function with itself let's normalize
it let's normalize it
that means let's multiply it by a
constant so that the integral of s star
s
DX is equal to
one this is for momentum igen
functions size sub P for the same igen
value in other words equivalently let's
require that the total probability of
finding the particle anywhere adds up to
one anywhere on this
circle is just a statement the total
probability of finding it somewh on the
circle is
one all right what is scar s if s is
given by this what is SAR
s it's just
one SAR s is just one so this says the
integral of one but what is the integral
over the integral goes from 0 to 2 pi
r from 0 to 2 pi
r of one is certainly not equal to
one not it's equal to 2 pi
r so in order to get this to come out to
be one we have to multiply the wave
function by the square root one over the
square root of 2 pi r
it's just a number it's just a numerical
number that happens to depend on R and
if we do that then s star s is just 1
over 2 pi r this becomes integral of 1
over 2 pi r from 0 to 2 pi r and now it
is equal to
one this is just something to keep track
of that it's uh convenient to normalize
these wave functions so that they Norm
so they in a product with themselves is
equal to one doesn't play any great role
in what I'm going to say but it's nice
to uh get the formulas
right
okay what about the inner product
between wave functions with different
values of
P say p and
Q if p is not equal to Q well then the
answer is zero and you can check that
just by knowing the properties of
exponentials like this but the reason
that we know it is because the igen
vectors of Herm Mission operators with
different igen values are always
orthogonal so this is a this is
something that you can check that the
integral of e to the I PHX e to the
minus I qhx or whatever that that's
equal to zero but that follows from the
Herm Mission property of the operator p
which we checked last time we checked it
last time by working
out uh the property of being her
Mission okay so now we have the wave
functions for these particles but
there's something we haven't uh we
haven't guaranteed yet we haven't
guaranteed this periodicity here thus
far a general wave function like this is
not necessarily
periodic the space of states that we're
interested in is the space of periodic
wave functions so let's ask what is the
constraint what do we have to do to
restrict ourselves only to those wave
functions which come back to themselves
well the answer is that if we take e to
the i p h
barx and we add to x 2 pi
r that it had better just
be e to the I p over HR
X in other words after X makes an
Excursion of 2 pi r it must come back to
itself that's the condition of
periodicity it's the condition that the
wave function is really on a circle and
not on a
line all right well this is equal to of
course e to the i p over HR x * e to the
i p over HR * 2i r just the property of
exponentials and that has to be equal to
e to the i p over HX we can cancel this
out and our rule is that e to the i p
over
HR * 2 pi r must be equal to
1 that's a restriction on the possible
values of
momentum that's a restriction on the
possible values of the igen
value so that we actually are in the
appropriate space of
functions if we choose P to be anything
other than something which sets us equal
to one it's not an allowable wave
function because it's not periodic it's
not really on a
circle the condition that this is equal
to one is the same as saying that P over
H bar * 2i R has to be an in multiple of
pi e to 2 pi n where n is any integer
time I is equal to
one and only if n is an integer is this
equal to one e to 2 pi I is equal to 1 E
to 2 pi I to the N power is equal to 1
and so the general
solution uh to uh requiring the wave
functions to be periodic is that P over
HR * 2 pi r should be an integer
multiple of 2
pi we can cancel out the 2
pi we can divide by
r r is just the radius of a circle and
what it tell and we can multiply by H
bar it tells us that the allowable
values that the moment can take on are
integer multiples of h/ R let me write
let me clean that up the allowable
values of the mo of the momentum are
integer multiples now I forgot what I
said integer multiples of what H bar
over
R if we choose any other values of p in
this wave function it won't be periodic
and it will not correspond to motion on
a c
so what we learn among other things is
although the position on the circle is a
continuous variable the momentum is a
discrete variable the momentum is a
discrete variable and it can only take
on Integer multiples of a certain
quantity H over R now as the circle gets
bigger and bigger as R gets what what's
the uh let's uh let's plot the possible
values of
P here they are they're
discret Nal 0 could be over here n = 1
Nal 2 but the values of P are n * H bar
over R so that means the
separation between different vales is
not a separation in space it's a
separation of the um possible values of
momentum they're separated by amount H
bar over
r as R gets bigger and bigger if we well
if we imagine a bigger and bigger
Circle which means that this line goes
from zero to some very very large size
then the spacing between the different
values of momentum gets smaller and
smaller and eventually any value of
momentum or very dense values a very
dense collection of momentum become
possible
so by making the circle very very
big and tending toward the situation
where it becomes an infinite line in
that
limit the momenta the possible momenta
become anything but if we're actually on
a circle if we're actually talking about
a particle moving on a circle then the
momenta are quantized quantized means
that they come in integer multiples of
some particular value of
momentum that's the AR that's always the
origin of discreetness in quantum
mechanics uh discreetness of various
things which In classical mechanics can
take on any value and in quantum
mechanics only take on discrete values
energies and things like that always has
to do with some periodicity and the wave
function having to be
periodic Let's uh go one step
further let me just remind you from
classical mechanics if we have a
particle moving on a
circle it has an angular momentum the
angular momentum is called
L we worked it out last quarter and it
can be written in a number of ways but
one way that it can be written is the
tangential component of
momentum let's just call it P it's the
component of momentum along the circle
which we've called
P times r
angular momentum is momentum time
distance or the moment arm of the
momentum what does that say the possible
values of angular momentum are the
possible values of angular momenta are
R that's this R here times the possible
values of P which is nhh over
R so we see before our very eyes that
angular momentum is quantized in units
of H incidentally angular momentum and H
bar have the same
units uh units of length times uh times
momentum action it's called angular
momentum comes in integer multiples and
it doesn't matter how big the circle is
however big the circle is the size of
the circle canceled out of this and we
found out quite independent of the size
of the circle the angular momentum is
quantized angular momentum always comes
in discret integer multiples of uh
except when it comes in half integer
multiples but that's another story for
another
day
okay angular momentum is quantized in
quantum
mechanics what happens what should we do
when the circle does get very big
the circle is a
convenient uh starting point for
studying particle on an infinite line
just by making the circle bigger and
bigger and bigger eventually
approximates a particle on an infinite
line but as I said in that limit the
Spectrum the collection of igen values
of momentum becomes denser and denser in
other words it approaches a
Continuum the discrete spectrum of of
momentum becomes
continuous what was the spacing between
different momenta it was H bar over
r h bar over R was the spacing between
the different momenta here and as R gets
bigger they get denser and denser and in
that limit we start to use the Continuum
notation instead of
describing uh instead of describing
vectors P which have inner products
which are chronica deltas we stretch
them out we stretch them
out and P and Q represent two different
momenta and use the direct notation P
minus
Q in the limit where the um where the
line gets so big that basically every
value of the momentum is possible in
that limit we want to think of the
momentum as a continuous variable
and just use the notation of direct
Delta functions we don't really do
anything new we just uh stretch out the
vectors by one over the square root of
this distance here stretch them out and
replace the chronica Delta by the direct
Delta there's not much physics in this
replacement of the chronica Delta by the
direct Delta it's just a convenience and
a trick uh to be able to pretend that
this is a continuous function which it
is not of course
as our bits uh tends toward Infinity
would you then expect the regression
back towards classical mechanics no not
well in in one respect only in the
respect in the respect that the possible
values of momenta become
anything but that does not mean we go
back to classical mechanics
necessarily in fact we'll discuss that
right now
yeah in the angular momentum If I
multiply P *
r p * R is angular momentum so the
spectrum of angular momenta the r cancel
out in the spectrum of momenta it
doesn't yeah good right
okay angular moment momenta just differ
by this factor of
R and it's just definition of angular
momentum but it's a good definition of
angular
momentum so the quantization of angular
momentum ultimately has to do with the
periodic nature of the angle variable
the angle around the origin here is
clearly a periodic variable wave
functions have to be period even if
you're not on a long even if you're not
restricting yourself to motion on a
circle even if you can move anywhere in
space still when you go around a closed
loop here the wave function has to come
back to itself and that's the content
that's the ultimate content of the
quantization of angular
momentum that if you rotate around by 2
pi you come back to yourself you come
back to the same
thing all right now all right so now I
was asked the question are we
essentially doing classical mechanics
when we uh when we let the interval go
to Infinity no not at all um In
classical
mechanics a particle can have both a
known position and a known momentum in
other words it can be in a state in fact
every state of a particle has both a
position and a
momentum uh with infinite Precision
position and
momentum are simultaneously
specifiable not so for a quantum
mechanical
particle
specifying the position of a particle
means choosing an igen Vector of its
position operator the position the igen
vectors of the position operator
correspond to the states in which the
particle has a very very definite
position the igen vectors of the
momentum operator correspond to the
states where the particle has a definite
momentum the IG states of
position are these high narrow functions
that look like that what about the igen
states of
momentum they have the
form e to the ipx which means let's uh
this the thing in the denominator here
is not so important they have the form
of
cosine p over
HX plus I sin P
HX each one of these functions is more
or less uniformly spread around the
Circle if we tend to let the circle get
an infinitely Big Radius it means
they're infinitely spread over the
entire axis why do I say they're
infinitely spread well the easiest way
to see it is just to take s star Time s
the magnitude of the function it's just
one it doesn't vary on the circle so
each momentum state has equal
probability of being anywhere is on the
circle each one of the momentum States
separately has equal probability of
being anywhere on the
circle okay each position state is
extremely well localized in
space so
no wave function is simultaneously an
igen Vector of position and
momentum just can't have any for which
the position and the momentum are both
specified so we're not doing classical
mechanics we're quite far from classical
mechanics but let's discuss a a little
bit the idea of simultaneously
specifiable two variables are called
compatible if you can specify both of
them uh
simultaneously position and momentum are
not compatible in that uh in that sense
what is the condition that let's say we
have two observables A and B I think I
called The Operators with little hats on
top of them supposing I have two
operators A and
B which are simultaneously
specifiable what does that mean that
means that they have common igen vectors
that means that there are igen vectors
which are igen vectors of both of the
operators
simultaneously in fact the best possible
situation for two operators being
completely compatible is that if all of
the or if there is a complete basis of
vectors let's label it
I'm going back to the discrete case but
it doesn't matter that there's a
complete basis of vectors which are
simultaneously igen vectors of both A
and B then each one of those igen
vectors both A and B can be specified
and can be uh can be definite so if we
have a complete set of igen
vectors for which both A and
B we have a complete set of IG vectors
which are simultaneously igen vectors of
a and of B then A and B are compatible
and they can both be
known by simply putting the system into
one of these combined igen
States well let's see what that means
that means we have a complete basis of
vectors labeled from 1 to capital N such
that for every one of
them a on N is some igen value let's
call it Alpha subn *
n this just says that these vectors are
all igen vectors of a with igen value
alpha
n the first Vector has IG value alpha 1
the second one has igen value Alpha 2
but simultaneously the same set of
vectors exactly the same set of vectors
are also I vectors of
B with I value let's say beta n * n
the necessary the question is what is
the necessary conditions necessary in
fact and sufficient conditions that two
operators A and
B have the same set of igen vectors so
in order to motivate the conditions
let's let's study what happens if you
multiply a * B and then act on N what
does that do
well we know what B does when it acts on
N it just gives us the igen value beta n
* n so we can rewrite this as
a times the number beta n now this is a
number beta n is not an operator anymore
times
n beta n is just a
number we can take it out put it on the
left hand side of the uh of the operator
a and so that becomes beta n a *
n numbers ordinary numbers you can push
them back and forth at
will uh they just multiply the vector n
by two and using the linearity of a we
can easily just move beta to the other
side now what is a on
N that's alpha n * n so what do we get
we just get beta n Alpha n * n in other
words the same set of vectors are igen
vectors of the product a * B with igen
values which are just the
products but we can also see from this
that it doesn't matter which order we
multiply A and B if they have a
simultaneous set of igen vectors in
other words if there's a
basis which are simultaneous IG vectors
of both operators
then it doesn't matter which order we
multiply them because in any order we're
just going to get beta n * alpha n * n
the order that we multiply two ordinary
numbers is immaterial alphas and betas
are just numbers and it doesn't matter
if we write this as beta n alpha n or
alpha n beta
n and from that we see that the order
that we multiply A's and B's won't
matter if they have a complete basis of
common igen vectors all right the
necessary and sufficient conditions I
won't prove this but the necessary it's
clearly a necessary Condition it's also
sufficient the necessary and sufficient
conditions that there exist a basis of
vectors which are common IG vectors of
both simultaneous igen vectors of both
are that a *
B is equal to B * a
that's necessary and sufficient another
way to write it is a * B minus B * a is
equal to
Z now remember A's and B's are operators
they're not numbers in
general but if they're compatible if
they're compatible then it doesn't
matter which way you multiply them and
the symbol for ab minus ba is called the
commutator
ab the bracket this is not a bra and a
cat the square bracket with A and B
sandwiched inside it with a comma that's
by definition
AB minus
ba so with all of this little bit of
notation the necessary and sufficient
condition for two operators to be
compatible is that they commute that
their commutator is
zero this of course is not not always
true for every pair of operators but
when it's not true they don't have a
complete set of common igen vectors and
they're not compatible you can't in
general measure both of them or you
can't know both of them
simultaneously uh what about position
and momentum are they compatible well
from what I told you it's clear that
they're not there are no common igen
vectors none whatever all right so they
can't be compatible but we could check
this by checking whether position and
momentum commute in other words it
should follow that position and momentum
don't
commute if there are no common igen
vectors we can check that we can just do
the
calculation of multiplying P * x and x *
p and see if we get the same
thing so let's do
that and in the process we'll find out
exactly what XP minus PX is is not zero
so let's work it out here's what we want
to
calculate X XP minus
PX now if
we well
operators now remember what x does to a
wave function it just multiplies it by x
what does p do minus i h d by DX
so we can write this as x * - i d by
DX
minus- i d by
DX * X all I've done is substitute for p
minus i d by DX but what on Earth does
this mean you're not allowed to just
write d by DX you have to D by DX has to
do something to to a function so let's
take this
and see what it does to a general
arbitrary
function let's try to figure out what
this operator is by seeing what it does
when it operates on a general function
so let's take this
thing
xus I D by
DX minus now we just can minus time
minus is plus plus I D by
DX * X
and apply it to a function of x s of X
now it makes
sense now it makes sense the first term
here is just X oh what did I leave out H
bar H H bar multiplies the whole
thing okay H Bar times the whole
thing x * - i d by DX Time s of X
remember when you multiply operators
ab and you apply them to vectors you
first apply B and then you take what you
get and you apply a to
it okay so here it is we first apply
minus i d by DX to S let's take these
two terms and work them out separately
first of all we get H and then this term
gives us X
minus I DC by
DX all I've done here is apply this D by
DX to
S the x is to the left so it doesn't get
differentiated only the S gets
differentiated and then we multiply it
by
X in the other term we have plus
I H
and now first we hit s with X that means
we have x * s of X and then we
differentiate the whole
thing what's the derivative of x * s of
X we have to work that
out the derivative of x * of X has two
terms in one of them the derivative hits
X and leaves s in the other one the
derivative hits s and leaves X so just
this piece of it here
iar gives us DX by DX that's 1 * s of
X Plus x d s by
DX this is just differentiating the
product X x side so there an IH bar
and another I
here let's see what we have we have
minus I xdc DX and then we have plus I
xdc by DX they cancel in other words the
term that you get when the derivative
hits s cancels this one here so that
cancels we can just forget this and
forget
this all that's left over when you do
this operation is i h s of X so here's
what we learned we learned that
XP or just uh let's just yeah
XP minus
PX when you think of it as an operator
hitting any wave
function just multiplies the wave
function by
iar in other words this thing does
exactly the same thing as multiplication
by a simple number a simple complex
number
iar one writes this by saying that the
commutator of X and
P XP minus PX is equivalent to or is
equal to multiplication by the number IH
bar XP minus PX is I bar now as a
classical equation that's nonsense
x * p is equal to P * X but as an
equation for operators operators don't
necessarily commute the order in which
you multiply them counts just like
matrix
multiplication what this is telling us
is
that X and P are operators which don't
commute and the worst possible situation
incidentally is when their commutator on
the right hand side is just a number
that's as bad as any uh commutator can
be
and it is the reason that there are no
common igen vectors at all there are no
common igen vectors if there was a
common igen Vector then at least if you
were to put that common igen Vector here
then at least when it acts on that
common igen Vector you would get zero
but there are no common igen vectors and
uh that's an indication of the fact that
the commutator is just a number
it's as bad as it can
be okay let's stop for a minute and
yeah vector vector every Vector is an
igen Vector of the commutator this is
true that is true with the same Ian
value yeah
true my address tells you there's no
information in the commutator I mean
there's no the commutator is not an
interesting observable Every Time You
observe it you get the same
number so okay so it's not that doesn't
tell you anything about the system I'm
talking about thinking of this as an
observable it doesn't tell you anything
about the system when you measure it XP
minus PX is always equal to IH bar in
classical physics it's always equal to
zero this was heisen B's crazy equation
XP minus PX is equal to I bar that
people thought he had lost his marbles
when he wrote it
down maybe he did lose his marbles but
in any case
uh it's a correct
equation another question
yeah com back way find back con I can
back
yeah
uh it seems like x
* x * any Vector is just x * that Vector
so why isn't vector vector no because X
is not a number yeah
okay here's here's what it would mean to
be an Vector you have some
function arbitrary
function and if you have an operator
which operates on that function and
gives you a multiple of that function
let's say two times that function then
it's just two times the same
function okay if the igen value is I
then it gives you I times the same
function if you multiply this function
by
X it doesn't give you the same function
back even a multiple of that function
function it gives you a function which
will look like
this because you're multiplying it by
something bigger over here than you are
over
here okay so for example let's suppose
this function were just e to Theus x s e
to- x^2 has a bell shape like that that
is not a numerical multiple of x * eus
x^2 okay the only igen functions of X
are Delta
functions because when you multiply them
by X only one value of x gets uh picked
out so it is multiplication by a number
for for a Delta function right so it's
not every function is a multiple of
every other function if you if you allow
variation in the in the uh in the
coefficient when we say it's an igen
Vector we mean with a numerical constant
coefficient here not an X put a three or
3 + 2 I or
whatever okay so that's
uh I knew that was going to come up I
was waiting for somebody to ask it thank
you okay so here's the setup
again we have two
slits now let's suppose we closed up one
slit closed up one slit and took a beam
of
particles coming through here described
by a wave function each the particles
are described by a wave function some s
of
X and the simplest thing would be to
have a s of X which was just for example
an e to the
ipx this would describe a particle with
momentum P coming in from the left we
yeah p over H
bar right the particle passes through
the hole
and a and the probability wave
s spreads
out like
that in fact I could even write down
what it is but I don't want to write
down what it is we'll just uh just draw
a picture of it all right now it hits a
screen and when it hits a
screen it's varying from here to here
for here to here it's a wave then has a
trough and a high point low Point High
Point low point and so forth when it
hits the
screen in the vertical Direction here we
also see variation we just see the
variation of the wave radially imprinted
on the screen as a variation along the
screen now if you think about it even if
this were even if these waves were
uniformly
separated like
so they would not look quite uniformly
separated on the vertical
screen they would look more closely
spaced up here than they do down here
just try it out take a a um compass and
a piece of paper draw some concentric
circles like that and you'll see that
they get more closely spaced up here
than they are
here if we were to approximate the wave
vertically uh
by an e to the I let's call it P over HR
y that wouldn't be such a good
approximation because the wavelength
varies as we move up and down the
wavelength is shorter up here than it is
here all right but let's just say over
some some interval so over some interval
it looks pretty much like an e to the I
P1
uh like
that uh some vertical variation
variation along the Y AIS here this is
the Y
AIS now let's open a second hole put the
second hole over here oh before we open
the second hole what is the probability
of finding the particle at different
values of Y now this is only a good
approximation for a small interval but
still for that small interval what's the
probability for finding the particle at
different
y it's uniform because if I multiply
this by its complex
conjugate I just get
one all right so the probability
vertically over some small interval
where the function can be approximated
like this is
uniform the magnitude of e to the i p
over H bar Y is constant
right now supposing we open a second
hole a second hole will also create a
wave similar kind of wave which will add
to the wave that comes out of
here so the wave that comes out of here
will get added to by a second wave which
comes out of
here what we're doing is we're taking
some State described by e to the I
py and we're adding to it another state
something we never do in classical
physics we never add States in classical
physics but we're adding a second Vector
this is a vector describing what happens
if the particle goes through the first
pinhole if the particle goes through the
second pinhole it creates a different
wave vertically
here and in fact the different wave up
in here has a slightly different
variation we could represent that by
saying the second wave that comes out of
here might look like e to the i q over
HR y over the same interval over the
same interval they have slightly
different
variation slightly different
variation because they're at different
heights vertically relative to the
hole so they have slightly different
variation now supposing you took either
one of
these either one of these has a
magnitude equal to one so if we only had
one hole opened vertically here over
some range of distances we would have a
uniform probability
distribution a probability distribution
which would not vary
vertically all right no variation
vertically in the probability
distribution if we only opened one hole
it might vary slowly but the
oscillations implied in this function
here would not cause any kind of
oscillation in the probability
because this thing squared the
oscillations go away
right okay what if we take the sum of
these two which is what happens
if we open both
holes another way to say it is if we
open hole number one we get out a wave
function s of X we get a state of s
let's call it si one if we open open
hole number two we we get outside
two if we open both holes the state of
the electron or whatever it is becomes s
1 plus S 2 in other words it becomes the
vector sum of the two states that it
started with the two states from the
individual
holes okay now let's
ask what the probability to find
different Y
is all we have to do is take this and
multiply by by its complex conjugate so
let's do it let me call this let's get
rid of the H bar let's work in units
where H bar is equal to 1 we get tired
of writing
it so it's e to the I
py plus e to the I
qy but then we have to multiply it by e
to the minus I
py plus e to Theus
iqy what have I done I've taken the wave
function and multiplied it by its
complex
conjugate okay if I only had one of
these then then the uh probability would
be uniform along the Y AIS either one
but now I have both of them let's
calculate
this e to the ipy * e to minus iy what's
that
one we also have e to the iqy * e to
Theus iqy that's also one
so the terms e to the I * e to Theus IP
and e to the IQ * eus IQ all together to
give us
two then we get
plus e to the i
py e to the minus I
qy that's coming from this term times
the far term over
here and then we have
plus e to the I
qy * eus I
py or to write it slightly
differently this is
twice e to the i p minus
qy 2+ excuse me
2+ plus e to the minus i e to the
i q minus
py what is this e to the I * something
plus e to the I * the negative of
that twice cosine twice cosine so this
becomes
twice 2 + 2
cosine of pus q y
2 + 2 cosine P minus qy or even
simpler just
twice 1 + cosine of P minus q
y what does this do is this constant no
it's not at all constant it has a
constant piece and it has an oscillating
piece the oscillating piece is just a
cosine
the oscillating piece the piece there's
one piece which is just one I'm
forgetting the two here there's one
piece which is just one and there's
another piece which is a cosine here's a
cosine of
something we add them
together where they enhance each
other they're twice as big where they
cancel each
other where the one cancels the cosine
the answer is zero in other words there
are places in this function where the
answer is
zero okay in fact what the sum of the
two functions looks like is it looks
like
this there are places where it goes to
zero what does that mean that means if
we open only one hole the probability
distribution is uniform
if we open the other hole the
probability distribution is uniform if
we open both holes there are places
where the probability is zero despite
the
fact that uh that particles could get
here quite easily if we opened only one
hole so opening both holes makes it
harder to get to this point here than
opening either one of the holes this is
the puzzle or the puzzling not the
puzzle but the puzzling phenomenon of
interference and it's a particle
phenomenon in other words it's a
phenomenon that happens even if we only
let one particle through at a time one
particle through at a time if we open
one hole we get a constant probability
distribution if we open the other hole
we get a constant probability
distribution if we open both holes we
suddenly find that there are places
where you can't get
to that's the
significance of adding
States
S Plus
fi S Plus F can have a complicated
dependence even though the probability
for S and fi might be perfectly
smooth so
interference oh notice notice how
important complex numbers were here well
I we've already we've already discussed
the importance of complex numbers in uh
in the momentum in and having a
momentum e to the I
p.x if we didn't have complex numbers we
could never have an igen Vector of minus
i d by DX
obviously okay
um questions let's stop for questions
now
yeah yeah the bigger the the bigger the
distance between the slits the closer
the spacing and the uh and the um
smaller distance between the splits the
bigger the spacing that I that's not yes
that is correct that is not what I
wanted to point out here though I just
wanted to point out that the phenomena
of interference has to do with the
ability to add State vectors which is
something you don't do in classical
physics but the answer is the closer the
slits the closer the slits the further
the interference pattern the bigger the
interference pattern the further the uh
slits the shorter the distance between
the interference Maxima and we can work
that out we work that out another day
yeah yeah if that's right that's right
that's
right yeah okay
so
[Music]
um if you let a wave go through a hole
and you project it onto a screen over
here what you'll
see oscillates it oscillates pretty much
like one of these Z to the
ipys but it oscillates with a changing
oscillation so for example over here
let's just take uh I'll draw it as an
oscillation of course it has a real and
imaginary part but the oscillation will
have a longer
wavelength over here than it does As you
move out the wavelength will get shorter
As you move out you know
why okay I'll tell you
why anybody have an
idea I mean you can just do it by
calculus you can take a wave going out
like this uh and calculate how uh how
close the uh the Maxima are when they
intersect but there's a physics point of
view also
how does the particle get over here it
gets over here by getting a kick in its
momentum so in order for it to get over
here it must have a larger vertical
momentum than over here right at the
center it required no vertical momentum
to get to here to get to here down here
it required a somewhat bigger vertical
momentum remember now the bigger the
momentum the faster these functions
oscillate the bigger P the faster faster
the functions oscillate so when you
actually plot the function that you get
from a wave going through a hole you
find out that pretty much anywhere it
looks like an ordinary wave except with
a slowly varying slowly modulated
frequency where the frequency gets a
little bit F uh yes a little bit faster
As you move away from the
hole now now you take the second hole
and you open it over here
all right at this point in this region
over
here
the vertical frequency due to one hole
is a little bit different than the
vertical frequency due to the other hole
because they're at different height here
okay so it's just like superposing
taking this wave and then superposing a
replica of it shifted you'll be adding
together two waves of slightly different
fre frequency just because from a single
hole the frequency varies As you move
vertically and that variation has to do
with the fact that to bend for the
trajectory to bend it has to pick up a
vertical component of momentum that
extra vertical component of momentum
makes it vary a little more rapidly down
here but you can work it out I can tell
you what the formula is if
you if a wave goes through a hole over
here and let's say that hole is at the
uh the vertical
origin then the wave that comes
out looks something like e to the i
p r is radial
distance divided by r r is radial
distance
here okay now let's put the screen in
here what is the radial distance to a
point that distance y what's the radial
distance from here to a point at
y Square let's call this
l r is the square
root of l^2 +
y² and what's down here is not so
important square otk of L2 +
y^2 here you can see that what goes on
here is not a simple plain wave e to the
I py but e to the I P times a function
which has a more complicated variation
if you take this function here you'll
find out that pretty much anywhere's
along here it looks like an ordinary
oscillation but the oscillation gets a
little bit faster as you go out here
gets a little bit faster but very large
y you can ignore
L and then it just looks like e to the
ipy but in close ER the variation is a
little bit different and so what you're
doing is you're putting together two
functions with slightly different um
oscillation
wavelengths well of course what we're
doing here is calculating beats these
are nothing but beats two slightly
different
frequencies are and now we're not
talking about time we're talking about
vertical height two slightly different
vertical frequencies are getting into
phase out of phase into phase out of
phase
and creating this uh this extra
oscillation with the cosine here that's
all this is is is Beats but beats in the
probability
distribution and it's coming
because the wave that comes out of a
state of the electron that emerges from
one hole here is some s which is
characterized by one wave function if
you open the other
hole you superpose a second wave
function which is characterized by a
shifted wave function and the sum of the
two of them has this oscillation that
neither one of them
has neither one of them has an
oscillation in the probability together
they have an
oscillation me is that the frown
defraction pattern what's that frown
defraction pattern I I don't know what
frown is what what is fr haer remind me
I forget what fren haer is it's just a
defraction p pattern yeah it's just a
it's a defraction pattern it's the
defraction pattern in this case of two
holes
right okay now somebody asked me about
um the the distance between the uh the
Maxima if the two holes are very close
together then you're adding functions
which are almost identical in that case
the p and the Q here are almost the same
okay if the p and the Q here are almost
the same it's like beating together two
almost equal
frequencies all right you get a very
very long wavelength uh so if the two
holes are close together then this
cosine here has a very long
wavelength if the two if the
um if the two holes are far apart then
you're beating together two waves with
somewhat different
frequencies and so you see a shorter w
wavelength for the uh or shorter
interval between the
Maxima any other questions
yes say it
again
okay we certainly have not gotten to it
yet because in order to get to it we
have to talk about a composite system
the composite system now being the
electri R plus the detector and talk
about the concept of
entanglement between the detector and
the uh uh and the
electron right so what being discussed
here which I'm not going to talk I will
talk about it but I won't uh I won't
derive it now because we have to
understand how to combine systems
together at the moment we're talking
about a single
electron or we're talking about a
sequence of experiments each one
involving a single electron uh um
supposing there was a object over here
which detected which of the holes the
electron went through now by detecting
which hole it goes through it means the
electron leaves an imprint on on
something it leaves an imprint on some
other
system telling that other system I went
through this hole or that
hole when that occurs the interference
pattern is destroyed but we're not in a
position yet to discuss that because we
have to discuss um entanglement before
we
do uh that incidentally was the subject
of the previous uh lectures on quantum
mechanics and it is in there but um
we'll try to discuss it a little bit
again okay so as I said this that's part
of the problem of combining systems
together the systems being whatever it
is that detects the electron and the
electron more complicated story
sorry deves from the horizontal you
mention that it gets a vertical and
momentum say it again now oh when the
particle deviates from the
horizontal has well in order for it to
deviate from the horizontal it must have
picked up some component of Y momentum
all right if it picked up a component
some significant amount of Y momentum or
another way to say it is if it doesn't
deviate from the vert it must have meant
that there was no y momentum and in fact
that must mean in this location over
here the function is varying
particularly slowly which it is all
right there's the slowest variation over
here in order for it to get out here it
must have gotten a kick to get a kick it
now has a y component of momentum and
the Y component of momentum means that
it has a certain oscillation over here
so where does the energy come from oh
there's no energy to change the momentum
the energy is proportional to the square
of the momentum and the square of the
momentum hasn't
changed um it's uh roughly speaking like
a bouncing well you have a you have a uh
a Target over here a stationary Target
which doesn't move and you bounce a ball
off it the ball changes Direction but
there's no loss of energy so that means
the X momentum would correspondingly
decrease yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
exactly that's right the mag magnitude
of the momentum the magnitude of the
momentum is determined by the distance
between these uh Maxima and Minima in
the radial
direction that is just the original same
spacing as the spacing that came in
spacing that goes out is the same as the
spacing that came in so the wavelength
coming in is the same as the wavelength
going out but it's converted into a
spherical wave but when projected when
projected onto the vertical axis you see
a variation in the uh in the frequency
vertically and that corresponds to
having picked up some uh some vertical
momentum and as you say that would also
imply that the horizontal component of
momentum must be a little bit less up
here than it is down here that's a good
point
uh no other question yes so a question
on on the so we have a bre far function
it's now hitting both hes that's right
the way function
right is it meaningless can talk about a
a corpuscular particle
going well we're sending through one
particle at a time out of the electron
gun one particle at a time is coming
through one particle at a time doesn't
make a wave like pattern like that it
just makes a spot on the
detector but we do it many many many
times
and we discover that there's a
probability distribution on the detector
here so each event consists of a spot on
the
detector it's only the accumulated
effect of many spots on the detector
that will create a pattern on here and
the pattern will be the pattern that
looks like
this notice one thing this is always
positive positive or zero is negative
nowhere cannot be negative that's
because we multipli The Thing by its
complex conjugate so the probability
distribution is NE never negative but it
does vary and it varies uh in some
places is equal to
zero yes how how does this compare to
like the interference of light well the
interference of light is a special case
light consists of a large number of
photons photons are particles they
satisfy the same rules as electrons if
we attenuate the beam of light for
example by sending it through a series
of filters which filter out almost all
the light then we'll find out that very
few photons are coming through and what
we'll see is a flash a flash a flash a
flash eventually building up to the
pattern of uh of the of the wave likee
interfer appearance if on the other hand
we send a lot of light through all at
once well then we'll just see the uh the
probability distribution as a uh as a
pattern sort of created all at once but
that's just because a lot of particles
came through all at the same
time so uh we see the particle aspects
if we slow not we don't slow the
particles but we
um uh number yeah we decrease the number
so that the coming through one at a time
let's say 10 years between photons and
we see a blip every 10 years well they
come through randomly but let's say on
the average once every 10
years then we see a blip but if we wait
a thousand years then those 10 years per
blip blips add up to a uh add up to a um
an interference
pattern so as I said we're not going to
explain strange Quantum phenomena but
but this is the description of
it yes I'm still having trou with the
one hole experiment and trying to
understand where the oscillation comes
from the The Limited oscillation you see
somehow well you don't see an
oscillation from just one
hole um what do you see on the screen or
what's the problem the distribution of
probabilities on the screen from one
it's just a blob it is a blob yeah
okay uh right in the all right what you
the question is what does a wave
function look like so let me let me uh
roughly write down what the wave
function looks
like it looks like an e oh boy I I
must remember to tell them to put fresh
pens can can that be seen not very well
I'm afraid all
right probably red is better than uh
blue I imagine let's try
it we're talking about one hole right
one hole so basically for one hole you
see some kind of e to the
I
uh from some function of X which is not
exactly x uh PX but it's something like
PX uh times a
another function let's call it row of X
where this is a rather smoothly varying
thing this is a smoothly slowly varying
thing oh I should I should call this y
let's call this why
why all right so there's some
oscillation multiplying something which
is not oscillating very fast roughly
speaking it looks like e to the
ipx p over h barx
times some smooth function row of
X incidentally p over H is likely to be
a rather large number which means that
this oscillation is generally very fast
this row of X is a smooth function which
doesn't vary very much over the r over
the range here now what happens if we
multiply this by its complex conjugate
if we multiply and this is a real
function this is real this is here's
where the imaginary Parts come if we
multiply this by its complex conjugate
then this goes away and we just get row
of
X2 okay and row of x^2 is a nice smooth
function and we see no oscillations from
one hole being opened up y row of
Y row of Y I keep writing X but I keep
meaning
y row of
Y now if
we and of course as I said this isn't
exactly e to the I py you can think of
it as a slowly varying p as you vary up
and down here so there's a p which
varies slowly as you vary As you move up
and down here times a nice smooth
function but then you open a second hole
and the second hole is some e to the I
let's call it P prime or
Q over H bar
y times another smooth function a second
smooth function row of Y where the
second smooth function might just be the
first smooth function slightly
displaced okay slightly displaced
because you lowered the hole either one
of these if you were to square them you
would not see the
oscillation but when you add them
together and square it then you see the
Beats between the uh between these two
things so
one by itself you see no uh no
interference
pattern yeah okay right all right it
depends you see something that depends
on the details of the hole Okay now
what's yeah it's it's a good point and
let me just uh spell it
out if the hole has rather sharp
edges right then what you see is a wave
coming out of here but you also see a
wave that got produced right at the edge
the sharp edge created a little wave
around the sharp edge and the other
sharp edge creates another wave around
the sharp edge and it's almost as if you
had two holes if the edge is not so
sharp if it's a kind of fuzzy hole then
it doesn't uh it doesn't create an
interference pattern then the
interference pattern of the single hole
is not there it's true a single hole can
make a uh an interference pattern by
scattering off the two uh by scatter
scattering off the different parts of
the Hole uh and that's correct yeah yeah
but it's quite distinct from this it's a
different uh right right yeah you see
some circles but the circles are
different than the interference pattern
that you see because of the two
holes right mhm so in the two-hole
situation shooting one electron through
at a time they places on the screen will
never be that's right two holes
are yeah watch Spot forever there'll
never be any
spot now I mean nothing is ever quite
that good I mean uh there's a bit of an
idealization here but this is
essentially correct yeah there's dark
spots which are can be very very dark if
you uh if you have good tiny tiny
[Music]
holes and everything is very very
ideal h
no cosmic rays no uh no no noise in the
room everything is uh you know as ideal
as possible then you can see some pretty
dark interference uh spots in there and
those dark interference spots
are for uh in an idealized situation
there would be no particles sitting
there
yeah the two holes are at the same
size um as long as the two holes are
small
small if the two holes are small then it
really doesn't matter whether they're uh
identical or not if one hole is big and
the other is small then of course it'll
make a difference but uh separ yeah
small compared to the separation right
and the wavelength it's also important
that everything yeah it's also important
that everything be small compared or
small or not too much bigger than the uh
than the wavelength of the
light yeah I I say electrons but if you
were to do this experiment in the
laboratory you'd want to use
photons
yeah uh photons have much longer
wavelength I mean light ordinary light
has wavelength many many times longer
than the typical wavelengths that you
can make for electrons it's hard to make
long wavelengths for
electrons but uh in principle if you
could uh if you could create electrons
with long wavelengths you could do
pretty much the same thing long
wavelength what does long wavelength
mean it means very low momentum very low
momentum means very slow right how do
you make very very slow electrons it's
not so easy because where do you get
electrons from you get electrons out of
hot wires for example the hot wires
eject the electron with some velocity
how do you get very very very slow
electrons not so easy to get them so if
you want to make long wavelength you
want very slow and it's not so easy to
get very slow
what's
that for electrons yes oh uh you need to
make the slits very very small and very
very close together to see this that is
true so even even optically even
optically you uh you need to make the
slits pretty close
together uh you can they're visibly
close together they're not so close
together that you can't see them but uh
but you need to make the course yeah
independent of the source if you change
the source and you still get the same
effect if you change yeah yeah pretty
yeah you get the same Source you see
yeah you get the same effect um once the
electron comes out of the hole here it
pretty much forgets what it was doing
over here and it just becomes an
electron which was produced over here it
becomes an electron which was shot out
from that
point that's the IDE idealization that
you can approximate the electron as an
electron ejected from exactly that point
or exactly that
point an electron ejected from this
point or from this
point uh add up to a wave which has this
kind of interference pattern yeah
there's a way to bring the same electron
back say it again if there's a way to
bring the same electron back it still
would get the same if it was a way to
send the electron back once it has gone
out yeah the same electron somehow be
cycled back
the through the hole
here wait you want to cycle the electron
through one hole and back through the
other no you can do it from the screen
the first issue of
reversibility
oh oh oh oh oh you want to know what
would
[Music]
happen if the electron passed
through and then you reversed everything
is that what you're asking if you
recorded it on the screen oh yeah and
that that actual electron somehow could
be come back through well
um you could imagine that the electron
bounces off the screen leaves a little
spot there and bounces off and then you
could uh of course you could then try to
focus that electron back through the
hole you could do
that and you would get the same kind of
pattern on this
side no you want a
cyron no I don't think you want a
cyron you can use the same electron over
and
over you can use the same electron over
and over you can collect the electron
from here bring it around bring it
through the hole whatever you want and
do the experiment over again with the
same electron oh yeah you can definitely
you can use another electron or you can
use the same
electron last time you told us that if
you if you detect it then that changes
it if you don't detect it if you detect
it over here that changes it yeah oh no
if you detect it at the
hole
ah okay um
let's come back that you you now you're
asking the question about
reversibility that's a different
question than whether you can use the
same electron over and over for the same
experiment
okay all right let me come to that next
time let me come to that next time it
involve in fact let me come to that
after we talk about hamiltonians we have
to understand hamiltonians and evolution
before we can answer that question yeah
[Music]
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu